Hello, and welcome back. Before we continue with sparse modeling,
欢迎大家回来 在我们继续讲稀疏建模前
I want to make a side note on the topic of Compressed sensing.
我想顺便提一下压缩感知这个话题
Compressed sensing, basically, is using some of the same concepts that we have
压缩感知 用到了我们之前学过的某些概念
been learning. But its goal is not to model a signal to
但其目标不在于模拟或表示一个信号
represent a signal, but the goal is to provide a new
而是提出新的模式
something or a new sensing paradigm. Let us explain that.
或新的感知范例 让我来说明一下吧
We have, as we have before, a signal x, and we are going to consider that the
与之前一样 我们有一个信号x
signal is exactly what we have seen before.
我们假设这个信号和之前见到过的一样
A dictionary multiply by a sparse vector. So, this is the signal that we want to
可以用一个字典乘以一个稀疏向量来表示 这就是我们想感知的信号
sense. In compressed sensing, we multiply that
在压缩感知中
by a matrix that reduces the number of rows.
我们将其与一个行降维矩阵相乘
So, we had a signal which was N dimensional and we are going to represent
这样我们就得到一个N维信号
it as dictionary times a sparse vector. But, we are not going to sense N points,
并且将其用字典乘稀疏向量来表示 但是我们不是要去感知N个点
we're going to sense the product of these Q matrix with x, and Q is what's called a
而是要感知矩阵Q与x的积 而Q是一个胖矩阵
fat matrix. So, it has, here, it has N.
它有N列
But here, it has less than N. So, we are in a sense less that's why
但是行数少于N 我们需要感知的内容少了 这就是称其为压缩感知的原因
it's called compressed sensing. Now, let us write that down in formulas.
让我们把这写成公式
We have D alpha equal x, that's what we have here.
先前已经说过 Dα=x
But we multiply both sides by Q, the sensing matrix.
两侧都乘以感知矩阵Q
So, Q times D defines a new dictionary, this D tilde, is kind of a new
Q乘D定义了一个新字典 即D~
dictionary, times alpha, the same sparse vector is equal not to x but to x tilde,
再乘α 得到的稀疏向量不是x 而是 x~
the sense vector which is shorter than it was before.
新的感知向量比原有的要短
So, we end up basically sensing less points.
结果是我们只需要感知更少的点
And the goal is to recover from this, which is what was sensed, and the
我们的目标是 从被感知到的x~和已知的D中恢复数据
knowledge of D, because we know the sensing matrix, we know the dictionary.
因为我们知道感知矩阵 故也能知道字典D
The goal is to recover alpha. So mathematically, this looks very
我们需要恢复出α 从数学上看
similar to sparse modeling. We have a signal, we have a dictionary
这跟稀疏建模非常像 利用已知信号和字典
and we need to reconstruct alpha. Now, what compressed sensing does, it
来重建α 而压缩感知所做的
deals with this fundamental problem. And basically, the idea is to provide
是解决这个基础性的问题 总的来说
conditions for the recovery to be possible.
这种思想是提供成功重建的条件
The conditions have to be on Q, the sensing matrix, they have to be on D, the
这些条件与感知矩阵Q
dictionary that we use for the sparse representation.
稀疏表征字典D
And also, on the level of sparsity of alpha.
稀疏参数α 都有关
So, compressed sensing provides very nice mathematical theory.
所以说 压缩感知提供了一个非常好的数学理论
And conditions under which we can do the recovery.
和实现重建所需的条件
If we can recover alpha from the sense x tilde, then we will be able to recover
如果我们能从x~中恢复α
the original signal x by doing D alpha. And, once again, the same way that we
那我们也能由Dα得到原始信号x
have a lot of interesting math in sparse modeling, there's a lot of related math
与稀疏建模里很多有意思的数学内容一样
in compressed sensing that provides conditions for this to be possible.
压缩感知里面也不少相关的数学知识让其可以实现
But, it's very important to make a clear distinction.
但是 分清这两者还是很重要的
What we have been discussing about sparse modeling is the model of signals.
我们讨论稀疏建模的时候是指信号模型
Compressed sensing is about designing new sensing protocols.
而压缩感知是设计新的感知协议
Now, for what type of signals with a sign new sense in protocols?
那么 对什么样的信号我们会设计一个新感知协议
Most of compressed sensing has been dealing with the design of new sensing
大部分压缩感知都在为稀疏信号设计新的感知协议
protocols for sparse signals. Meaning, signals that can be represented with a
也就是那些可以用稀疏字典来表征的信号
dictionary in a sparse fashion. So, those use the same type of tools but
所以这两者使用了相同的工具 但是目的不同
they're very different goals. And basically, what compressed sensing is
压缩感知试图扩展Nyquist理论
trying to do is trying to extend Nyquist, which is a classical sampling or sensing
Nyquist理论是一个经典的带限信号取样或感知的理论
theory for band limited signals. Compressed sensing says, what should be
压缩感知探究的是
the sampling or sensing theory for sparse signals?
稀疏信号的采样或感知理论是怎样的
And that's the relationship between compressed sensing and sparse modeling.
这就是压缩感知与稀疏建模的关系
After this very short note on compressed sensing,
在这一小段有关压缩感知的内容后
and we could spend weeks teaching about compressed sensing but it's not the topic
我们可以用几周的时间来讲述压缩感知的相关知识
of this week or of this, of this class. But, after this short note, we're going
但这并不是这一周甚至不是这门课程的主要内容
to come back in the next video with one more concept in the area of sparse
下一节课我们将继续讨论稀疏建模领域的几个概念
modeling. See you then.
到时候见
Thank you very much.
非常感谢